Guide to the Carnegie Endowment for International Peace records,
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
- Series I. Secretary's Office
  - Subseries I.C: Board of Trustees, 1910-1943
    - Sub-subseries I.C.2: Meetings-Verbatim transcripts, 1910-1943
      - 1920-1912 (Box 12)
      - 1913-1919 (Box 13)
      - 1920-1930 (Box 14)
        On microfilm: #2002-1007 (1920-1926) and #2002-1008 (1927-1930)
      - 1931-1945 1931-1939 (Box 15)
        on microfilm: #2002-1008 (1931-Dec 1932) and #2002-1009 (Dec 1932-1939)
      - 1946-1947 (Box 16)
    - Sub-subseries I.C.3: Executive Committee, 1911-1948
      The Executive Committee determined the manner in which the books and accounts of the corporation were kept and examined the accounts and vouchers of the Treasurer for moneys either received or paid out by him. This Committee submitted a written report to the Board of Trustees at each meeting of that Board and submitted an annual report at the annual meeting of the Corporation. (Source: Carnegie Endowment for International Peace: Summary of Organization and Work. Washington DC: CEIP, 1941 pp12)
      - Minutes, 1911 1927-1930 1935 1937-1940 1942-1948 (Box 16)
      - Correspondence, 1925 1935-1948 (Box 17)
    - Sub-subseries I.C.4: Trustee files, 1912-1948
      - Alexander, Wallace Mck., 1936 1938 1939 (Box 17)
        Correspondence concerns: Institute of International Relations, Dr. Chitoshi Yanaga exchange of materials, Institute of Pacific Relations, nomination of trustees.
      - Ballantine, Arthur A., 1936 1937 1938 1939 1941 1946 1947 (Box 17)
        Correspondence concerns: election to board, republican party platform, exchange of materials, Greater N.Y. Federation of Churches, Green Cover reports, Francis White.
      - Bancroft, Edgar A., 1924 (Box 17)
        Correspondence concerns: University of Louvain, exchange of materials.
      - Barrows, David P.
        Correspondence concerns: exchange of materials, election, Seventh Annual Scientific Congress, visit to Germany, Institute of International Relations, nominations.
        - 1929-1933 (Box 17)
        - 1935-1941 (Box 18)
      - Bell, James. F, 1939 1942 (Box 18)
      - Brookings, Robert S., 1925 1926 (Box 18)
        Correspondence concerns: economic conditions, National Conference on International Problems and Relations, nominations, newspaper articles.
      - Bullitt, William Marshall, 1934 1936 (Box 18)
        Correspondence concerns: Republican party platform, nominations, American Library Association.
      - Bundy, Harvey H., 1948 (Box 18)
      - Burke, Judge Thomas, 1925 1926 (Box 18)
      - Catlin, Daniel K. (Box 18)
      - Chapin, William Wallace, 1939 1941 1944 1945 1948 (Box 18)
      - Cherrington, Ben M., 1942-1946 (Box 18)
        Correspondence concerns: William Haas, appointment to trustees, National Option Research Centers, Atomic Energy.
      - Davis, John W., 1927 1929 1930 1931 (Box 18)
        Correspondence concerns: incorporation of trustees, Russian emigrants, Lord Craigmyle, illness.
      - Davis, Norman H., 1931-1939 (Box 18)
        Correspondence concerns: election, Disarmament Conference, Foreign Policy Associations, exchange of materials.
      - Delano, Frederic A., 1925-1943 (Box 19)
        Correspondence concerns: Pan-American Conference, American Civic Association, criticism of Endowment's policies.
      - Dulles, John Foster, 1944-1947 (Box 19)
      - Evans, Lawton B., 1929-1933 (Box 19)
      - Fox, Austen G., 1927-1937 (Box 19)
      - Franks, Robert A., 1929 (Box 19)
      - Fraser, James Earle (Leon), 1938 1939 1942 (Box 19)
        Correspondence concerns: election to trustees, American Historical Association.
      - Freeman, Douglas, 1937 1938 (Box 19)
      - Gaines, Francis Pendleton, 1933-1947 (Box 19)
      - Hamlin, Charles S., 1926-1935 (Box 19)
      - Harrison, Earle Grants, 1947 1948 (Box 19)
      - Heinz, Howard, 1926-1938 (Box 19)
      - Hill, David Jayne, 1926-1932 (Box 19)
      - Holman, Alfred
        Correspondence concerns: reports on various trips to Latin America and Europe, nominations, policy.
        - 1926 (Box 19)
        - 1927-1929 (Box 20)
      - Houghton, Alanson B., 1932-1938 (Box 20)
      - Howard, William, 1929 (Box 20)
      - Jessup, Philip C., 1937-1946 (Box 20)
      - Lansing, Robert, 1922-1926 (Box 20)
      - Lowden, Frank O., 1932-1939 (Box 20)
      - Manning, Richard T., 1931 (Box 20)
      - Molyneaux, Peter, 1935-1945 (Box 20)
      - Montague, Andrew J., 1924-1935 (Box 20)
        Correspondence concerns: Paris trips, Interparliamentary Union, Chinese students.
      - Morris, Roland S., 1931-1946 (Box 20)
        Correspondence concerns: League of Nations, peace movements, Americans of Japanese descent, death.
      - Morrow Dwight W., 1925-1930 (Box 20)
      - Olds, Robert E., 1925-1930 (Box 20)
      - Parker, Edwin B., 1929 (Box 20)
      - Peters, William A., 1929 (Box 20)
      - Pritchett, Henry S., 1925-1939 (Box 21)
        Correspondence concerns: executive committee, China, nomination, monument for La Place (French mathematician), Egypt, finances, Butler's European tour, world court, Institute of International Education, request for resignation, acceptance, death.
      - Reed, Philip D., 1948 (Box 21)
      - Rockefeller, David, 1948 (Box 21)
      - Root, Elihu, 1924-1939 (Box 21)
        Correspondence concerns: Japanese relations, nomination, Geneva trip, Alexander Hamilton's papers.
      - Ryerson, Edward L., 1933-1944 (Box 21)
      - Schieffelin, William Jay, 1941-1944 (Box 21)
      - Sheffield, James R., 1925-1938 (Box 21)
      - Sherman, Maurice
        - 1929-1933 (Box 21)
        - 1935-1947 (Box 22)
      - Sibley, Harper, 1938-1948 (Box 22)
        Correspondence concerns: YMCA, Church World Service.
      - Smiley, Albert Keith, 1912 (Box 22)
        In Memorium certificate.
      - Smith, Jeremiah, 1932 (Box 22)
      - Strawn, Silas H., 1926-1946 (Box 22)
        Correspondence concerns: policy, nominations.)
      - Taft, Robert A., 1935-1937 (Box 22)
        Correspondence concerns: elections policy, League of Women Voters.
      - Wadsworth, Eliot, 1937-1948 (Box 22)
      - Wakefield, Lyman E., 1943 (Box 22)
        Correspondence concerns: election.
      - Watson, Thomas J., 1935-1948 (Box 22)
        Correspondence concerns; International Chamber of Commerce, European trip, South American trip, policy, nominations.
      - Waymack, W. W., 1941-1948 (Box 22)
        Correspondence concerns: Economic Policy Committee, election, appointment to Atomic Energy Commission.
      - Wriston, Henry M., 1943-1946 (Box 22)
  - Subseries I.D: Depository Libraries, 1936-1949 (1 box)
    - Most of the publications of the Endowment were sent to a carefully selected list of libraries geographically distributed throughout the world and several important centers of population and education. The Endowment hoped to supply the public with the results of its research and investigations through these libraries. In 1941 the depository list totaled 926 of which 446 were in the United States. (Source: Carnegie Endowment for International Peace: Summary of Organization and Work. Washington DC: CEIP, 1941 pp15-16.) This subseries includes correspondence, policy memoranda distributed to the libraries by the Endowment, and some printed material. (Box 23)
  - Subseries I.E: Financial, 1910-1949
    (11 boxes, 2 vols)
    Subseries I.E. is organized into the following subseries:
    1. Accounting and Finance
    2. Staff
    3. Grants
    - Sub-subseries I.E.1: Accounting and Finance, 1920-1949
      (This subseries includes correspondence and documents. The correspondence regards audits, ledger accounts, receipts and disbursements, general business matters, salaries, honoraria, appropriations, and allotments.
      The documents include summaries of receipts and disbursements, balance statements and summaries, resolutions of the finance committee, auditor’s reports, treasurer’s reports, finance committee meeting agenda, finance committee meeting minutes, and schedules of securities.
      - Correspondence: (Box 23)
        - 1920 1923 (Box 23)
        - 1924-1937 (Box 24)
        - 1939-1943 (Box 25)
        - 1944-1947 (Box 26)
      - Documents: (Box 26)
        - 1936-1946 (Box 26)
        - 1947-1949 (Box 27)
    - Sub-subseries I.E.2: Staff, 1910-1911 1926-1947
      This subseries contains material relating to applications for employment, retirement, salaries, notices of resignation, letters of recommendation, staff policies, sick benefits, compensation, War Labor Board, and other matters dealing with the staff in general.
      See also III.B. Topical Volumes (volumes 97-98).
      - Applications for employment: (Box 27)
        - 1910-1911 (Box 27)
        - 1926--1947 (Box 27)
      - Individual Staff: (Box 28)
        - Ursula Hubbard (Duffus), 1932 1938-1943 (Box 28)
        - Mary Winn, 1937 (Box 28)
      - General, 1911-1949 (Box 28)
      - Payroll Sheets and Vouchers, August 2, 1912 -- December 31, 1913 (Box 28)
    - Sub-subseries I.E.3. Grants, 1915-1949
      In its first years of operation, the Endowment made grants (often referred to as subventions) in support of institutions and initiatives working for peace. Soon after World War I, the Trustees decided to devote all of the Endowment's resources to undertakings that they would initiate. An inevitable result of this decision was the gradual reduction and eventual termination of grants to other organizations.
      This is a sampling file in chronological order covering the years 1912-1949. The file comprises requests for grants from various organizations and individuals and the Endowment's answers to these requests. Most of the requests made were not supported. The records documenting the Endowment's support of certain organizations can be found in Series VI. Organizations and Series VII. Projects. Other requests for support are filed in Series III.B. Topical volumes (volumes 99-119).
      - 1915-1926 May (Box 29)
      - 1926 June -1930 Feb (Box 30)
      - 1930 March-1931 (Box 31)
      - 1932-1939 (Box 32)
      - 1940-1949 (Box 33)
      - Published literature from applying organizations (Box 34)
  - Subseries I,F: Incorporation of CEIP, 1928-1930
    It was decided by the trustees of the Endowment that it was propitious to secure a legal incorporation of the Carnegie Endowment for International Peace in order to give the trust stability, permanence, and well-established forms of legal supervision. The Incorporation became law on February20, 1929.
    After the passage of this bill several trustees felt the need for the passage of a short supplementary act to cover the point that the stipulations of Mr. Carnegie in his original letter of gift to the unincorporated trustees should not in anyway be subject to alteration by reason of the charter powers of the incorporated. This bill became law on February4, 1930. (Source: Carnegie Endowment for International Peace: Summary of Organization and Work. Washington DC: CEIP, 1941.)
    This subseries includes correspondence between the law office of Worcester Williams & Saxe, and Butler concerning the progress of the construction of the bill for incorporation, letters to and from Butler concerning the progress of the bill in the New York Legislature, correspondence between trustees concerning the creation of a new act to specify the transference of Carnegie's funds to the new corporation, copies of both the bill of 1929 and the bill of 1930 and copies of the minutes of the trustee meeting on February10, 1930.
    - Two folders (Box 34)
  - Subseries I.G: Library of CEIP, 1925-1950
    (2 boxes)
    The General Library of the Endowment was maintained as part of the Washington office under the supervision of the Secretary. It contained 64,000 volumes. An annual appropriation was made for accessions. The Library was catalogued according to the Library of Congress system. Its major subjects were the peace movement, international law and policy, international arbitration, American and European history and diplomacy, and political science.
    A chronicle of International events was composed daily from newspaper, periodicals, and other documents. This chronicle was a ready source of information concerning any event of importance happening anywhere bearing on international relations. Bibliographies on subjects of current interest in the field of international relations were compiled in the Library and supplied to regular mailing lists. Bibliographic and other information was also supplied by mail and the telephone. The Library was open for free use by properly interested persons. Inter-Library loans with the Library of Congress and other important libraries were arranged. Permanent reading permits were issued to regular patrons. (Source: Carnegie Endowment for International Peace: Summary of Organization and Work. Washington DC: CEIP, 1941 p17.)
    This subseries contains correspondence regarding donations and acceptances of books, book orders, personnel, bibliographical information, biographical information, library policy, publications of the Endowment, the UN, and the League of Nations, the Slip Orientation program; it also includes reports, articles, charts, and clippings. (For materials from the library see Series VIII. CEIP Library.)
    - 1924-1946 (Box 34)
    - 1947-1950 undated (Box 35)
  - Subseries I.H: Officer files and correspondence, 1908-1951
    (28 boxes)
    Subseries I.H. is organized into the following subseries:
    1. Nicholas Murray Butler
    2. James T. Shotwell
    3. Charles Alger Hiss
    4. George Finch
    5. Henry Haskell
    6. Malcolm Davis
    7. Melvin Fox
    8. James Brown Scott
    9. Joseph E. Johnson
    10. E.N. Thompson
    11. Howard E. Wilson
    12. Anne Winslow
    - Sub-subseries I.H.1: Nicholas Murray Butler, 1908-1949 (7 boxes)
      - Correspondence: (Box 35)
        - 1908-1925 1929-1930 (Box 35)
        - 1931-1949 (Box 36)
        - Boyle, Sir Edward, 1942 (Box 36)
        - Bustamente, Antonio, 1947 (Box 36)
        - Capper, Arthur, 1929 (Box 36)
        - Carnegie Corporation grant, 1938 (Box 36)
        - Chamberlain, Joseph (Kellogg-Briand Pact), 1929 (Box 36)
        - Davies (Lord), 1938 (Box 36)
        - de Wendel, Maurice, 1934 (Box 36)
        - European matters, 1930 1939-1940 1946 (Box 36)
        - European trips, 1926-1931 (Box 36)
        - Gaiger, Philippe, 1931-1932 (Box 36)
        - Kellogg, Frank, 1926-1929 (Box 37)
        - Military training, 1917 (Box 37)
        - Queensborough (Lord), 1932 1935 1942 (Box 37)
        - Roosevelt, Franklin D., 1944 (Box 37)
        - Sadler, W.F., 1932 (Box 37)
        - Sakatani, Y. (Baron), 1926 1931-1933 (Box 37)
        - Sarfatti, Margherita, 1937-1946 (Box 37)
        - Sutherland, Millicent (Lady), 1941-1942 (Box 37)
        - Unwin, T. Fisher, 1925 (Box 37)
        - Visit with Pope, 1917 1927-1931 (Box 37)
        - Wilberforce, Robert, 1926 (Box 37)
        - World government contest, 1936 (Box 37)
      - Interoffice Memoranda:
        - 1933 (Box 37)
        - 1940-1941 (Box 38)
        - 1942-1945 (Box 39)
        - 1946-1947 (Box 40)
      - Secretary's notes of Conferences with Butler, 1912-1922 1939-1946
        - 1912-1917 (Box 40)
        - 1918-1922 1939 Jan-July (Box 41)
        - 1939 Sept-1946 (Box 42)
    - Sub-subseries I.H.2: James T. Shotwell, 1922-1951
      (5 boxes)
      This subseries contains correspondence, memoranda, speeches, articles, proposals, contracts, and Shotwell's diary for 1929. The material documents Shotwell's activities as an officer of the Endowment, but also reflect his engagement with other organizations and initiatives. (Material documenting Shotwell's work for the Endowment can be found throughout the Endowment's records, especially Series II. Division of Economics and History, and in two other collections held by the Rare Book and Manuscript Library: CEIP, Centre Européen Records and the James Shotwell Papers.)
      - 1922-1948 (Box 43)
      - 1949 A-S (Box 44)
      - 1949 T-Z (Box 45)
      - 1950-1951 (Box 45)
      - American Fund for Czechoslovakian Refugees, 1949-1950 (Box 45)
      - Butler, Nicholas Murray, 1925-1939 1941 1944-1945 1948 (Box 46)
      - Haskell, Henry:
        - 1923 1927-1933 (Box 46)
        - 1935-1940 1944 (Box 47)
      - Quetico-Superior International Peace Memorial Forest, 1945-1949 (Box 47)
      - Reports, Articles, Speeches, Proposals, Memoranda, 1931-1935 1938 undated (Box 47)
    - Sub-subseries I.H.3: Charles Alger Hiss, 1946-1949
      (7 boxes)
      Hiss's files include correspondence with various individuals and organizations, including the Twentieth Century Fund, American Friends Service Committee, Current Bibliography, Foreign Policy Association, Carnegie Corporation, Woodrow Wilson Foundation, The United States State Department, and Council on Foreign Relations. The correspondence deals mainly with United States government policy, the United Nations, and requests for grants. The files also contain press releases, invitations, and clippings.
      - 1946-1947 March (Box 47)
      - 1947 April -October (Box 48)
      - 1947 Nov-Dec (Box 49)
      - 1948
        - A-C (Box 49)
        - D-S (Box 50)
        - T-Z (Box 51)
      - 1949 (Box 51)
      - American Association for the United Nations, 1948 (Box 51)
      - American Friends Service Committee, 1948 (Box 51)
      - Bloomfield, Daniel, 1947 (Box 51)
      - Bullitt, William Marshall, 1947 (Box 51)
      - Bunche, Ralph, 1947 (Box 51)
      - Butler, Nicholas Murray, 1946-1947 (Box 51)
      - Carter, Edward C., 1947 1949 (re Hiss trial) (Box 51)
      - Cherrington, Ben, 1947 (Box 51)
      - Committee for the Marshall Plan, 1948 (Box 52)
      - Citizens' Committee for Reciprocal World Trade, 1948 (Box 52)
      - Council on Foreign Relations, 1948 (Box 52)
      - Dennett, Raymond, 1947 (Box 52)
      - Dulles, John Foster, 1947 (Box 52)
      - Fox, Melvin, 1947-1949 (Box 52)
      - Herring, Pendleton, 1947 (Box 52)
      - Ives sub-Committee on Relations with International Organizations, 1948 (Box 52)
      - Johns Hopkins 71st Commemoration Day, 1947 (Box 52)
      - Monroe, Parker, 1947 (Box 52)
      - Pasvolsky, Leo, 1947 (Box 52)
      - Rogers, Alla H., 1948 (Box 52)
      - Shotwell. James T., 1947 (Box 52)
      - Staley, Eugene, 1946-1948 (Box 53)
      - State Department, 1948 (Box 53)
      - Stevenson, Adlai, 1947 (Box 53)
      - Thompson, E.N., 1948 (Box 53)
      - Tranoy, Erik, 1948 (Box 53)
      - United Nations, 1948 (Box 53)
      - United Nations Budget Study, 1947-1948 (Box 53)
      - Wadsworth, Eliot, 1947 (Box 53)
      - Waymack, W., 1947 (Box 53)
        re Atomic Energy Committee, National Farm Institute
      - Wilson, H.E., 1948 (Box 53)
      - Winslow, Anne, 1948 (Box 53)
    - Sub-subseries I.H.4: George Finch, 1923-1947
      - Inter-Office Correspondence (Box 54)
        - 1923-1938 (Box 54)
        - 1939-1947 (Box 55)
      - Bonnet, Henri, 1943 (Box 55)
      - Clark, Grover, 1936 (Box 55)
      - Cohen, Benjamin, 1945 (Box 55)
      - Darter, Oscar, 1946 (Box 55)
      - Dennis, William, 1946 (Box 55)
      - Dixon, Gertrude, 1943 (Box 55)
      - Dolan, Eleanor, 1947 (Box 55)
      - Eagleton, Clyde, 1945 (Box 55)
      - Endowment accomplishments, 1945 (Box 55)
      - Fahs, Charles, 1940 (Box 55)
      - Fox, Arthur, 1947 (Box 55)
      - Lemkin, Raphael, 1947 (Box 55)
      - Lockwood, William, 1941 (Box 55)
      - McMillan, Anne, 1947 (Box 56)
      - McNair, Arnold, 1946-1947 (Box 56)
      - Morris, George, 1947 (Box 56)
      - Pan-American Conference, 1942 (Box 56)
      - Proffit, Charles G., 1939 (Box 56)
      - Ranshofen-Wertheimer, Egon, 1945 (Box 56)
      - Ransom, William, 1947 (Box 56)
      - San Francisco Conference, 1945 (Box 56)
      - Suarez, Francisco. Fourth centenary of his birth, 1948 (Box 56)
      - United Nations Council of Philadelphia, 1947 (Box 56)
      - World Court, 1946 (Box 56)
      - Yale Anglo-American Project, 1943 (Box 56)
    - Sub-subseries I.H.5: Henry S. Haskell, 1917-1944
      - 1915 1917 1925 1930-1933 1936-1943 (Box 56)
      - Interoffice correspondence, 1933 1936 1938 (Box 56)
      - American Peace Award, 1934 (Box 56)
      - Current History, 1939 (Box 56)
      - Boussarie, F., 1936 (Box 56)
      - Close, Upton, 1935 (Box 56)
      - European trips, 1927 1929 (Box 56)
      - Giretti, Edoardo, 1931 (Box 56)
      - Hancock, Russell, 1944 (Box 56)
      - Hartley, Livingston, 1938 (Box 56)
      - Meyer, leland, 1932 (Box 56)
      - Nippold, Otfried, 1931 (Box 56)
      - OMarchevsky, Stoyan, 1932 (Box 56)
      - Sherman, Cynthia, 1933 (Box 56)
      - Vanamee, Grace, 1923 (Box 56)
    - Sub-subseries I.H.6: Malcolm W. Davis, 1922-1951
      (5 folders)
      These files include personal notes, speeches, manuscripts, and inter-office correspondence concerning the United Nations, Paris Office, Geneva Research Center, and Endowment policy
      See also Series III.C. European Centre
      - 1922 1932-1935 1941-1943 1946 1948 1949 (Box 56)
      - 1950-1951 (Box 57)
      - Wilson, Howard, 1945-1950 (Box 57)
    - Sub-subseries I.H.7: Phillip Jessup, 1931-1947
      - 1925-1926 1933-1942 (Box 57)
      - 1943-1947 (Box 58)
      - Clippings (Box 58)
      - Cooperation with the government, 1941-1943 (Box 58)
      - Finch, George, 1942-1943 (Box 58)
      - Foreign investments, 1940-1942 (Box 58)
      - International Law
        - 1939-1940 Sept (Box 58)
        - 1940 Oct-1946 (Box 59)
      - Legal problems in post-war planning, 1942 (Box 59)
      - Hunt Report, 1942-1943 (Box 59)
      - National Planning Association, 1931 1942 undated (Box 59)
      - National World Court Committee, 1931-1932 (Box 59)
    - Sub-subseries I.H.8: Melvin Fox, 1947-1949
      - 1 folder (Box 60)
    - Sub-subseries I.H.9: James Brown Scott, 1923-1940
      (11 folders)
      These files inlcude correspondence regarding the Divisions of Economics and History and International Law and publications, as well as inter-office memoranda, manuscripts of speeches and addresses, and booklets.
      - 1923-1931 (Box 60)
      - 1932-1940 1943 (Box 61)
    - Sub-subseries I.H.10. Joseph E. Johnson, 1950-1951
      - 1 folder (Box 61)
    - Sub-subseries I.H.11. E.N. Thompson, 1948-1949
      - 1 folder (Box 61)
    - Sub-subseries I.H.12. Howard E. Wilson, 1947-1951
      (14 folders)
      - 1947-1948 (Box 61)
      - 1949-1951 (Box 62)
      - Council on Student Travel, 1949-1951 (Box 62)
      - Great Debate, open letter on the, 1951 (Box 62)
      - Memorandum Letters, 1948 (Box 62)
      - National Conference of Christians and Jews, 1950-1951 (Box 63)
      - National Education Association, 1950-1951 (Box 63)
      - Report on trip to Scandanavia, 1950 (Box 63)
      - Syracuse University: UNESCO Conference (April 1950) (Box 63)
      - Webster, John R., 1948-1949 (Box 63)
    - Sub-subseries I.H.13. Anne Winslow, 1948-1951
      - 2 folders (Box 63)
  - Subseries I.I: Other Carnegie Organizations
    (6 boxes)
    Subseires I.I. is organized into the following subseries:
    1. Carnegie Corporation of New York
    2. Carnegie Dunfermline Trust
    3. Carnegie Foundation for the Advancement of Teaching
    4. Carnegie Hero Fund Commission
    5. Carnegie United Kingdom Trust
    - Sub-subseries I.I.1: Carnegie Corporation of New York, 1920-1941